Register of the Edward Teller Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Edward Teller Papers,
1910-2005
76074
Hoover Institution Archives
561 manuscript boxes, 49 oversize boxes, 10 open reel boxes, 3 cubic foot boxes, 2 card file boxes, 1 oversize folder, 2 album boxes, 11 slide boxes, 6 envelopes, 7 motion picture film reels, 8 phonorecords, digital files (287 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, reports, studies, memoranda, printed matter, photographs, motion picture film, video tapes, sound recordings, and memorabilia, relating to chemical, molecular and nuclear physics; development of new energy resources; national energy research planning; space exploration; and national and international security issues, including nuclear weapons and arms control.
Teller, Edward,
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1976,, with increments acquired through 2003.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collection(s)
A is for atom, B is for bomb: video tape, Hoover Institution Archives Ultimate weapon: the H-bomb dilemma video tape, Hoover Institution Archives Maria Goeppert Mayer Papers, Mandeville Special Collections Library, UC San Diego Leo Szilard Papers, Mandeville Special Collections Library, UC San Diego
Biographical Note
15 January 1908 Born, Budapest, Hungary
1926-1928 Student, Karlsruhe Technical Institute, Karlsruhe, Germany
1928 Student, University of Munich, Germany
1929-1931 Research associate, University of Leipzig, Germany
1930 Ph.D., University of Leipzig
1931-1933 Research associate, Guttingen, Germany
1934 Married Augusta (Mici) Harkanyi Rockefeller fellow, Copenhagen, Netherlands
1934-1935 Lecturer, University of London, United Kingdom
1935-1941 Professor of physics, George Washington University, Washington, D.C.
1941 Naturalized, Washington, D.C.
1941-1942 Professor of physics, Columbia University, New York City
1942-1943 Physicist, University of Chicago, Illinois
1942-1946 Physicist, Manhattan Engineer District of Columbia
1943-1946 Physicist, Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory, University of California, Los Alamos, New Mexico
1946-1952 Professor of physics, University of Chicago
1949 Author (with Francis Owen Rice), The Structure of Matter
1949-1952 Assistant director, Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory
1952-1953 Consultant, Lawrence Livermore Laboratory, University of California, Livermore, California
1953-1960 Professor of physics, University of California, Berkeley
1954-1958, 1960-1975 Associate director, Lawrence Livermore Laboratory
1958 Author (with Albert L. Latter), Our Nuclear Future
1958-1960 Director, Lawrence Livermore Laboratory
1960-1970 Professor of physics-at-large, University of California
1962 Author (with Allen Brown), The Legacy of Hiroshima
1963-1966 Professor emeritus and chairman, Department of Applied Science, University of California, Davis and Livermore
1968 Author (with Gerald W. Johnson, Wilson K. Talley, and Gary H. Higgins), The Constructive Uses of Nuclear Explosives
1969 Author (with Segre, Kaplan, and Schiff), Great Men of Physics
1970 Author, General Remarks on Electronic Structure and the Hydrogen Molecular Ion, and General Theory of Electron Structure
1970-1975 University professor, University of California
1972 Author, The Miracle of Freedom
1975 Author, Energy: A Plan for Action
1975- University professor emeritus, University of California Director emeritus and consultant, Lawrence Livermore Laboratory Senior research fellow, Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace, Stanford, California
1977 Author, Nuclear Energy in the Developing World
1979 Author, Energy from Heaven and Earth
1980 Author, The Pursuit of Simplicity
1987 Author, Better a Shield than a Sword: Perspectives on Defense and Technology
1989 Presidential Citizens Medal,
1991 Author, Conversations on the Dark Secrets of Physics
1998 Awarded a Magyarsag Hirneveert Dij, the highest official Hungarian government award
2001 Author, Memoirs: A Twentieth-Century Journey in Science and Politics
2002 Department of Energy Gold Award
July 2003 Awarded the Presidential Medal of Freedom
9 September 2003 Died at his home on Stanford campus
Scope and Content of Collection
Edward Teller was a nuclear physicist whose work was instrumental in the development of the hydrogen bomb. His papers, which document his life and career, include correspondence, speeches and writings, reports, studies, memoranda, printed matter, photographs, motion picture film, video recordings, sound recordings, and memorabilia related to chemical, molecular and nuclear physics; development of new energy resources; national energy research planning; space exploration; and national and international security issues, including nuclear weapons and arms control.
The majority of the material was received as an increment to the original collection, with documents originating from offices at the Hoover Institution, where Teller was a fellow, and Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, an organization which Teller helped to found and where he later served as director. The original accession contains Correspondence with Hans Bethe, Cresson Kearny, Nelson A. Rockefeller, and Lewis Strauss, as well as documents concerning the Commission on Critical Choices for Americans.
Born in Hungary in 1908, Teller received his Ph.D. while studying in Germany. In 1935, he immigrated to the United States, where he became a professor at George Washington University and was later employed at Los Alamos National Laboratory as a member of the Manhattan Project. During his career, Teller taught at various universities and authored several books. The Incremental biographical file contains book-length works written about Teller's life, as well as a booklet created from an exhibit on Teller at the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory. The file also includes calendars and documents related to Teller's birthday celebrations. See the Incremental oversize material for a scrapbook of letters given to Teller upon his retirement and certificates awarded to Teller.
The incremental correspondence is arranged in three series based on provenance of material. The Incremental general correspondence includes letters of Teller's family members, in addition to correspondence from both offices where he worked. The Incremental Hoover Institution correspondence contains letters of Hans Bethe, Sidney Drell, Freeman Dyson, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Henry A. Kissinger, Eugene Wigner, and Lowell Wood, as well as autograph requests that Teller received. The Incremental Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory correspondence as well as the Incremental Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory alphabetical file include letters related to Teller's scientific work, political advocacy, and business dealings. The correspondence regarding his professorial work is related to his research at Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory and his position at the Department of Applied Science, a joint program of LLNL and the University of California, Davis. In addition, these series include correspondence with colleagues at other research facilities, especially from Los Alamos National Laboratory. The bulk of Teller's political papers fall into two categories: correspondence with public figures regarding his support for the development of a thermonuclear deterrent arsenal and anti-ballistic missile defense systems, and documents related to his position on various governmental advisory boards and committees. For additional correspondence, see also the research files for Teller's memoirs.
The Incremental Hoover Institution alphabetical file consists of files on political and scientific topics, mainly relating to nuclear weapons. This file contains material on the atomic bomb, nuclear reactors, radiation, and the Strategic Defense Initiative.
Teller maintained two offices, one at the Hoover Institution and one at Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory. The Incremental general office file consists of Teller's calendars, documenting a hectic schedule that required him to switch between his two offices and travel frequently. Additional schedules and correspondence can be found in the Incremental Hoover Institution office file, which documents Teller's working life as a Hoover Institution fellow. The Incremental Lawrence Livermore Office file contains a publicity file that includes news stories concerning Teller, interview correspondence, and autograph requests. Teller's extensive lecturing and consultation work required frequent travel, and this aspect of Teller's life is particularly well-represented in the travel file.
In addition to publishing numerous scientific papers, Teller wrote on issues of defense and the use of nuclear weapons. The Incremental general speeches and writings contain drafts and working material for several of Teller's monographs, as well as for the unpublished work Technology in Warfare. The Incremental Hoover Institution speeches and writings include files on Teller's speeches for various organizations and venues, while the Incremental Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory speeches and writings consist of a chronological file of Teller's writings.
While working on his memoirs, Teller gathered correspondence of significance written and received over his long career and, along with his editor Judith Shoolery, conducted interviews with people who played a role in his life. The research material in the Incremental memoirs file includes correspondence of notable scientists and politicians such as Hans Bethe, Niels Bohr, Freeman Dyson, Barry Goldwater, Werner Heisenberg, Herbert Hoover, Lyndon B. Johnson, Leo Szilard, and Harry Truman, as well as research material related to Project Plowshare and Teller's time as a professor at the University of Chicago. In 1954, Teller testified in a hearing concerning the security clearance of J. Robert Oppenheimer, a physicist who served as an adviser to the Atomic Energy Commission. Teller's testimony provoked responses from members of the scientific community who felt that his testimony was a factor in the decision to revoke Oppenheimer's security clearance. The most extensive files on Oppenheimer in the collection can be found in the research files for Teller's memoirs.
Teller was an active proponent of Project Plowshare, a government program that aimed to use nuclear explosions for peaceful purposes, such as canal construction. The Incremental Project Plowshare file includes materials on Project Chariot, which was an attempt to construct a harbor in Alaska using nuclear explosions, and the Kra Canal. For addition material on Project Plowshare, see also research materials used for Teller's memoirs.
Throughout his career, Teller served in a variety of professional roles, including as a professor, consultant, and member of various boards. The Incremental professional activities file documents several of these roles, including his position at the Department of Applied Science, a UC Davis program conducted at Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory. In addition, this file includes information on Teller's involvement in the Hertz Foundation and the Edward Teller Center for Science, Technology, and Political Thought.
The Incremental writings by others series contains monographs inscribed by various authors such as Richard Nixon and Henry Kissinger, as well as writings by members of Teller's family.
The Teller papers include a sizable amount of audio-visual material. There are Incremental photographs of Teller at various stages of his life and photographs of Teller accompanied by prominent figures such as Ronald Reagan and Andrei Sakharov. Also included are digital photographs available on the computer workstation in the Hoover Archives reading room. The Incremental sound recordings and Incremental video recordings include recordings of Teller's speeches and interviews, as well as of Teller playing the piano. Several transcripts of recordings are interspersed within these series. Also included are Incremental motion picture film, containing an interview of Teller, and Incremental computer discs, containing data on Uranium.
Arms control.; Energy policy--United States.; Moving-pictures.; Nuclear energy.; Nuclear weapons.; Phonorecords.; Phonotapes.; Physics.; Slides (Photography).; Space sciences.; United States--Armed Forces.; United States--Defenses.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Politics and government.; Video tapes.
- Biographical File, 1954-1989 (Text 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Article, correspondence, get-well cards, schedules, clippings, and guest book, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Article on Edward Teller by Robert Coughlan, Typescript (intended for publication in Life Magazine), 1954 July 27. (Text 1, Folder 1)
  - Guest book of event honoring Edward Teller's 75th birthday (Text 2)
  - Get-well cards, 1989 April (Text 3)
  - Subject file - Australia. Correspondence, schedules, and clippings relating to Edward Teller's trip to Australia and visit with Lang Hancock in, June 1981 (Text 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Text 5)
- Correspondence File, 1954-1987 (Text 2-4)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General (Text 2, Folder 1)
  - Adams, Lofty A., 1982-1983 (Text 2)
  - Antonelli, John W., Jr., 1977-1978 (Text 3)
  - Applegath, Albert W., 1979-1984 (Text 4)
  - Bandtel, Kenneth C., 1979-1984 (Text 5)
  - Bethe, Hans A., 1954 (Text 6)
  - Billman, Kennteh W., 1979 (Text 7)
  - Black, Edwin F., 1984-1985 (Text 8)
  - Bund Gegen Anpassung, 1989 (Text 9)
  - Courant, R., 1954 (Text 10)
  - Davenport, James F., 1980-1983 (Text 11)
  - Fercsey, John, 1980 (Text 12)
  - Fermi, Laura, 1954 (Text 13)
  - Glanzberg, Al (New Mexican), 1955-1963 (Text 14)
  - Harrison, Donald C., 1986-1987 (Text 15)
  - Hefner, Robert A., III, 1978-1982 (Text 16)
  - Heppenheimer, Thomas A., 1984-1985 (Text 17)
  - Hickey, Jack, 1984 (Text 18)
  - Kearny, Cresson H.
    - 1980 (Text 19)
    - 1981-1983 (Text 20)
    - 1984-1986 (Text 3, Folder 1)
  - Konnyu, Ernest L., 1985 (Text 2)
  - Libby, Leona M., 1974-1984 (Text 3)
  - Makk, Americo, Eva, and A. B., 1983-1985 (Text 4)
  - Mehnert, Klaus, 1978-1983 (Text 5)
  - Menges, Constantine C., 1980 (Text 6)
  - Metzger, H. Peter, 1978-1980 (Text 7)
  - Mizuki, Mikiso, 1984 (Text 8)
  - Owens, Gwinn, 1975-1983 (Text 9)
  - Rainsbury, Rebecca, 1976 (Text 10)
  - Renz, Peter, 1984 (Text 11)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson A., 1975-1979 (Text 12)
  - Seifritz, Walter, 1980-1982 (Text 4, Folder 1)
  - Stewart, G. W., 1954 (Text 2)
  - Strauss, Lewis L., 1954 (Text 3)
  - Symons, William, Jr., 1978 (Text 4)
  - Younger, Evelle J., 1978-1980 (Text 5)
  - Zakkay, Victor, 1980 (Text 6)
- Speeches and Writings, 1954-1987 (Text 4-10)
  Articles, book drafts and manuscripts, interviews, and speeches, arranged chronologically by title
  - "The Development of the Hydrogen Bomb," Typescript, 1954 October 7. (Text 4, Folder 7)
  - Appearance, Youth Wants to Know, National Broadcasting Corporation radio broadcast, Printed copy of transcript, 1955 August 7. (Text 8)
  - Our Nuclear Future (with Albert L. Latter), Typescript of draft entitled "Atoms on the Loose", 1958. (Text 9)
  - "Outer Space Travel: What Is and Is not Possible?" Typed first page of book draft, 1960 October 19. (Text 10)
  - The Legacy of Hiroshima, Typescript, 1962. (Text 5, Folder 1)
  - Commencement speech, University of Cincinnati, Ohio, Typescript, 1962 June 10. (Text 2)
  - "Needed Now: Transatlantic ABM Defense and Union," Speech, International Movement for Atlantic Union, Washington, D.C. Printed copy, 1963 October 3. (Text 3)
  - "The Reluctant Revolutionary," Paul Anthony Brick Lecture, University of Missouri, Columbia. Printed copy, 1964. (Text 4)
  - Speech, Group of House Opponents of Proposed Atlantic Union Exploratory Convention, Washington, D.C., Typescript, 1974 July 31. (Text 5)
  - Energy from Heaven and Earth, Typescript of draft entitled "Adventures of Energy from Cradle to Adolescence", 1979. (Text 6)
  - Energy from Heaven and Earth, Typescript, 1979. (Text 6, Folder 1-2)
  - "The Energy Crisis: No Contingency Plan," Interview, World Research, Inc. Printed copy, 1980. (Text 7, Folder 1)
  - The Pursuit of Simplicity, Typescript, 1980. (Text 2)
  - Interview by John Singleton, Australia, Typed transcript of radio broadcast and call-in period, 1981 June. (Text 3)
  - "Free Enterprise and Energy from Heaven and Earth," Seminar, Council of Resources and Energy, Indooroopilly, Australia. Announcements, typescript, and typed transcript of question and answer period, 1981 June 12. (Text 4)
  - Speech on Energy from Heaven and Earth, Hoover Institution Book Talks, Stanford, California, 1982 January 12 (Text 5)
  - Better a Shield than a Sword: Perspectives on Defense and Technology, Typescript, 1987. (Text 8, Folder 1-6)
  - Better a Shield than a Sword: Perspectives on Defense and Technology, Typescript, 1987. (Text 9, Folder 1-13)
  - Better a Shield than a Sword: Perspectives on Defense and Technology, Typescript, 1987. (Text 10, Folder 1-15)
- Commission on Critical Choices for Americans, 1973-1976 (Text 11-18)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, essays, minutes, and membership and distribution lists, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - General (Text 11, Folder 1)
  - Background material (for Panel I) (Text 2-5)
  - Contributions by Michael J. Deutch (mostly for Panel I) (Text 6)
  - Correspondence and memoranda
    - General (Text 7)
    - For Panel I (Text 8)
  - Distribution lists (for Panel I) (Text 9)
  - Essays for Volume II, edited by Irving Kristol and Paul Weaver (Text 12, Folder 1-2)
  - Membership lists (Text 13, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of meetings of Panel I, 1973-1974 (Text 2)
  - Press release, 1973 November 18 (Text 3)
  - Reports (three of which were eventually published in Volume I). Includes some correspondence and comments
    - Panel I (Edward Teller was asked to write the panel's report, entitled "Energy: A Program for Action")
      - Undated fragments (Text 4)
      - 1973 (Text 5)
      - 1974 (Text 6-7)
      - 1974 (Text 14, Folder 1-2)
      - 1975 (Text 3-4)
      - 1975 (Text 15, Folder 1-6)
      - 1975 (Text 16, Folder 1)
      - 1976 (Text 2)
    - Panel II (Text 3-5)
    - Panel III (Text 6-8)
    - Panel V (Text 17, Folder 1)
    - Panel VI (Text 18, Folder 1-2)
    - Panel VII (Text 3)
  - Proofs (mostly of Panel I's report) (Text 4)
  - Review of 14-volume series (Text 5)
- Subject File, 1973-1984. (Text 19-34)
  Reports, studies, working papers, correspondence, notes, memoranda, testimony, statements, press releases, minutes, statistics, tables, printed matter, and maps, arranged alphabetically by topic
  - Agricultural research and technology (Text 19, Folder 1)
  - Ames Research Center, NASA (Text 2-3)
  - Arms control (Text 4)
  - Art and technology (Text 5)
  - Campbell, W. Glenn (Text 20, Folder 1)
  - Civil defense (Text 2)
  - Computed tomography in medical research (Text 3)
  - Educational Foundation for Nuclear Science (Text 4)
  - Energy
    - General (Text 5-7)
    - General (Text 21, Folder 1-4)
    - General (Text 22, Folder 1)
    - Australia (Text 2-4)
    - Biomass (Text 5)
    - Canada (Text 6)
    - Coal (Text 23, Folder 1)
    - Conservation (Text 2)
    - Consumption (Text 3)
    - Conversion devices (Text 4)
    - Developing countries (Text 5)
    - Fusion (Text 6)
    - Fusion (Text 24, Folder 1-3)
    - Gas. See also Petroleum (Text 4-6)
    - Geothermal (Text 7)
    - Helium (Text 8)
    - Israel. See Solar
    - Methanol (Text 9)
    - Nuclear (Text 25, Folder 1-5)
    - Nuclear (Text 26, Folder 1-2)
    - Petroleum (Text 3-5)
    - Portugal (Text 6)
    - Solar (Text 27, Folder 1)
    - Storage devices (Text 2)
    - Taiwan (Text 3)
    - United States
      - General - Carter's energy policy (Text 4)
      - California (Text 5-8)
      - New York (Text 28, Folder 1-3)
    - Wave. See also Australia (Text 4)
    - Wind (Text 5)
  - Energy and the environment (Text 6)
  - First Strike (television documentary) (Text 7)
  - Futurism (Text 8)
  - Holography (Text 29, Folder 1)
  - India (Text 2)
  - International Association for the Advancement of High Pressure Science and Technology (Text 3)
  - Meteorology (Text 4)
  - New York Times (Text 5)
  - Nuclear arms
    - Freeze (Text 6)
    - Proliferation (Text 7)
  - Nuclear safety and artificial intelligence (Text 8)
  - Nuclear wastes (Text 9)
  - Nuclear wastes (Text 30, Folder 1)
  - Oppenheimer, J. Robert
    - Transcript of hearing before the Personnel Security Board, United States Atomic Energy Commission, Washington, D.C., 1954 April 12 -May 6 (Text 2)
    - Statements issued by the Atomic Energy Commission, 1954 June 16 and 29 (Text 3)
    - Press conference held by director Norris E. Bradbury, Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory, Includes press releases, annotated by Edward Teller, 1954 September 24. (Text 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Text 5)
    - Clippings, 1954 (Text 31)
    - Magazine articles, See also Box 36, 1954 April-September. (Text 32)
  - Physics (Text 33, Folder 1-2)
  - Satellite remote sensing programs (Text 3)
  - Shell Oil Company (Text 4)
  - Space technology
    - Nuclear (Text 5)
    - Solar (Text 6)
  - Telecommunications in an energy crisis (Text 7)
  - Toth Aluminum Corporation (Text 8)
  - United States
    - Foreign relations - Taiwan (Text 34, Folder 1)
    - Politics and government
      - Presidential elections-, 1984 (Text 2)
      - Science Advisory Group meeting, Minutes, 1975 July 17. (Text 3)
- Printed Matter, 1954-1976. (Text 35-36)
  Journals, magazines, and book
  - Journals, magazines, and book (Text 35-36)
- Memorabilia, 1954-1973. (Text 37-45)
  Awards, citations, resolutions, medals, plaques, honorary degrees, and academic gown
  - Awards, citations, resolutions, medals, plaques, honorary degrees, and academic gown (Text 37-45)
- Audio-Visual Material, 1955-1995.
  Speeches, interviews, conversation and debate transcripts, and tributes, including some tapes by or concerning others. Consists of videotape cassettes, phonotapes, phonotape cassettes, microcassettes, magnetic tapes, and computer files arranged by physical form
  - Videotape cassettes (97)
    - Undated (Text 46)
    - 1976-1983 (Text 47)
    - 1983 (Text 48)
    - 1983-1988 (Text 49)
    - 1988-1992 (Text 64)
    - 1988-1989 (Text 50)
    - Includes typed transcript for interview of, 1989. 1989 August 25 (Text 51)
    - 1989-1990 (Text 52)
    - Includes transcript of an interview of G. Foster Evans, relating to relations between Teller and the physicist Stanislaw Ulam and to various aspects of economics and physics, 1990-1993. (Text 65)
    - 1991-1992 (Text 53, 64)
    - 1992-1995 (Text 65)
  - Phonotapes (44)
    - Undated (Text 54-55)
    - 1959-1972 (Text 56)
    - 1972-1975 (Text 57)
  - Phonotape cassettes (178)
    - Undated (Text 58)
    - 1959 (Text 65)
    - 1970s (Text 59)
    - 1980-1983 (Text 60)
    - 1986-1989 (Text 61)
    - 1990-1992 (Text 62)
    - 1993-1995 (Text 65)
  - Microcassettes, (5), 1983-1989 (Text 63)
  - Magnetic tapes, (2), n.d. and 1991
  - Computer disk, (1), n.d.